Guide to the Treasurer, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Correspondence, 1717-1940; Series III
  1717 - 1832 contains small amounts of correspondence from the administrations of John Prout, Roger Sherman, and John Trumbull, but the majority dates from the term of James Hillhouse. During Hillhouse'sincumbancy he also served in Congress, and while he was in Washington he depended on Stephen Twining, the assistant treasurer, to carry out the responsibilities of the office. Although the correspondence does include a few letters that Hillhouse wrote to Twining concerning the college'sfinancial business and events in Washington, most of the correspondence is actually Twining"s. Following Twining'sdeath in 1832 William G. Hooker served as acting treasurer. Several letters at the end of 1832 are addressed to him. The sub-series concludes with Twining'sletterbooks containing copies of his outgoing letters and notes on letters to be sent.
  The correspondence is arranged chronologically. Much of the correspondence is of a most routine nature concerning term bill payments, mortgage loans and payments, real estate negotiations, gifts to the college, collection of subscription pledges, letters from the contributors to the Benevolent Society or the Society for the Education of Indigent Pious Young Men, and occasional letters of parental protest concerning college discipline. John C. Calhoun sent two letters concerning his son's term bills, and Stephen Ball wrote concerning land sales in New Haven. Benjamin Hinman, a college agent, wrote concerning college land in Holland, Vermont. Between 1805 and 1807 Benjamin Silliman sent reports from Europe concerning his purchases of mathematical and optical apparatus. There are letters concerning the bequest of Elizabeth Talcott, the estate of Betsy Pratt, and the donation of Sheldon Clark. There are also several documents concerning the suit brought against the university by Daniel Potter and others on behalf of the Congregational Society of Plymouth. The society had invested in the failed Eagle Bank, a project which had Yale'sbacking. See also the correspondence with Asa Bacon on this suit. On February 2, 1832, John Trumbull wrote concerning drawings for the proposed Trumbull Gallery.
  Letterbooks contains all bound copies of outgoing letters from 1833-1906. (Letterbooks belonging to Stephen Twining (1806 - 1832) are in 1717 - 1832 ). These volumes contain either handwritten or letterpress copies. They are arranged in chronological order. There are no gaps between volumes, but it seems that the files are not complete before 1890.
  Financial Agents' Correspondence encompasses the letters received by the college'sfinancial agents, who were active in the various fund raising campaigns, between 1817 and 1841. Most letters concern the Centum Mille Fund. Chief among the agents of this fund was Wyllys Warner who traveled extensively. A letter from President Jeremiah Day gives him advice where to travel: "I have never had any high expectations of aid to the college south of Baltimore; or perhaps I ought to say New York." Warner also received correspondence from the other fund agents. Especially interesting is a report by Seth Bliss on his travels. Warner'scorrespondence as agent ends in 1832, though the Centum Mille Fund drive continued beyond this date. Since Warner was made treasurer in 1833, similar letters concerning fund raising activities addressed to him between 1833 and 1840 are filed in the sub-series 1833-1840.
  Of interest also in Financial Agents' Correspondence are letters to David Daggett about fund raising for the law professorship and letters to Chauncey Goodrich about the Gibbs professorship and theological fund. Henry L. Ellsworth wrote Goodrich respecting his plans for a sizeable donation. Of particular note is a letter to Benjamin Silliman from Thomas S. Grimke declining to contribute to the Centum Mille Fund because of his concern for the state of property and credit "among us." His letter reflects his concern about what the passage of South Carolina's nullification of tariffs might mean for the future.
  1833-1840 begins with one folder of letters addressed to William G. Hooker, who served as acting treasurer after the death of Stephen Twining and later in the absence of treasurer Wyllys Warner. In fact there are several letters from Warner detailing his travels. Since Hooker was also in charge of the art gallery there are several letters to him concerning the Trumbull Gallery and donations to it. A letter from Jared Sparks concerns a portrait of Major Andre. The folder also contains occasional copies of Hooker's outgoing letters.
  Following the folder of Hooker correspondence are all letters addressed to treasurer Warner. The letters are arranged in alphabetical order with the letters from a small number of select correspondents filed individually. Much of this correspondence is routine, being the usual letters concerning subscription pledges, mortgage negotiations, payment of college bills, and letters from renters, lawyers, and executors. The select correspondents tend to be those whose letters are more significant or more voluminous. Thus letters from long term renters may be filed under the name of the correspondent rather than in the general file.
  There are many letters from field agents raising funds for the college. Amos S. Chesebrough, an agent who travelled across Connecticut, wrote, "I have seen the "Adventures of a Traveler," the "Confessions of a Schoolmaster," and "Caleb in Search of a Wife," but I think that a volume entitled," An Agent in Pursuit of Money," would be as replete with incidents as any of them. The agents, Erastus Colton, Darius Mead, Thomas Perkins, and Mason Whiting traveled through New England and New York and wrote of their experiences. A sentiment common to their letters was "things look dark here."
  Among other interesting letters are those from William Lawrence concerning college land in Norfolk and from Mills Olcott concerning property in Vermont received through Dr. Nathan Smith's mortgage. There are many letters from John Trumbull, most merely acknowledging the quarterly payment of his annuity. William G. Hooker's letters to the absent Wyllys Warner describe the day to day functioning of the treasurer's office. At the end of the sub-series is one folder of correspondence of others which is addressed to neither Warner, Hooker, nor any college agent yet concerns the finances of the college.
  The correspondence for the period 1841-1888 covers part of the term of Wyllys Warner and the complete terms of E. C. Herrick and Henry Colt Kingsley. The quantity of correspondence for this period reflects the rapid growth of the college. There is a noticeable increase in quantity after the Civil War, and one may attribute this partly to Yale's increased interest in investments and land holdings in the developing West. The reader will note that there is very little correspondence from 1886-1888. During this time President Dwight served as acting treasurer, assisted by L. E. Osborn, and it is possible that some treasurer's correspondence found its way into Dwight's presidential or personal papers.
  1841-1888: General, consisting almost entirely of incoming letters and only occasional copies of outgoing letters, is divided by year and is arranged alphabetically within each yearly division. (For outgoing letters of this period see the sub-series Letterbooks. ) This correspondence contains much that is routine and deals with the treasurer's standard responsibilities: students" term bills, loans and mortgages, rent collection, real estate purchase and upkeep, college expenses, building plans, and legal problems involved in gifts and estates" settlements. There are also many subscriptions for the various fund raising campaigns such as the Library Fund, the Woolsey Fund, the funds to purchase Judge Hitchcock'slibrary and to erect a statue to Benjamin Silliman. The correspondents tend to be alumni, parents of students, faculty members, benefactors, salesmen, potential borrowers, debtors, tenants, real estate agents, brokers, insurance agents, merchants, and lawyers.
  Because E. C. Herrick for a period served as both treasurer and librarian, some correspondence addressed to the librarian is also filed in this sub-series. No attempt has been made to separate those letters concerning gifts to the library, requests for catalogues and copies of obituary records, or information on book orders and subscriptions.
  Correspondence of selected individuals from this period has been collected and segregated and now comprises 1841-1888: Select. A sizeable number of letters from Russell Sturgis, the architect for several buildings on the Old Campus, are included in this sub-series. Other campus architects represented here include Richard Hunt and Peter Wight. (Correspondence from Frederick Withers, George Hawthorne, and J. A. Mould, ca. 1866-1868, all unsuccessful entrants in the chapel competition, will be found in 1841-1888: General. )
  Correspondence concerning several notable gifts should also be noted. Under the will of Henry L. Ellsworth Yale inherited extensive property in Indiana. There is much correspondence from Elizur Goodrich as trustee of this estate. In 1878 Timothy Dwight Porter conveyed to Yale, subject to an annuity, a block in Manhattan bounded by 36th and 37th Streets and Lexington and Third Avenues. The files are filled with correspondence concerning the transfer and the mortgage and rental of this property. See especially the correspondence with Thomas Thacher and Theodore W. Dwight. Correspondence with Joseph Sheffield concerns another important gift, that providing for the Sheffield Scientific School. Other correspondence relating to special gifts will be found under the names of James Jackson Jarves, Frederick Marquand, and John Trumbull.
  During this period the treasurer shared some of his increasing responsibilities with faculty members in the various schools. Thus there is correspondence with Benjamin Silliman concerning financing scientific improvements, with Simeon E. Baldwin and Francis Wayland concerning the law school, with John F. Weir concerning the school of fine arts, with Robert Brown concerning the observatory, and with C. A. Lindsley concerning the medical school.
  1888-1901 consists of the complete incoming letter files of William Whitman Farnam and partial files of Morris Franklin Tyler. Cashier William C. Rowland also received some of the more routine letters in this correspondence. This extensive run of letters, originally filed alphabetically in 37 chronological letterboxes is now arranged in one alphabetical order with individual files for selected correspondents interspersed throughout. The topics discussed in these letters are much the same as those in the 1841 - 1888 sub-series though the quantity of letters is nearly six times greater.
  Predominant among the select correspondents are the names of investment counselors, real estate agents, and bankers, who assisted the treasurer in the increasingly complex task of managing the university'sincome producing funds. The largest amount of such correspondence concerns the firm of Peabody, Houghteling, & Co., but much investment correspondence will be found with the firms of: Baring Brothers; Cammann & Co. concerning management of New York City real estate; N. P. Dodge & Co.; W. T. Hatch & Sons; Lewis Investment Co.; E. S. Rouse; and Winslow, Lanier, and Co.
  The treasurers of the period also oversaw a major building campaign. Consequently the names of several prominent architects and firms (Cady, Berg & See; Carrere & Hastings; Walter B. Chambers; E. E. Gandolfo; Charles C. Haight; Howells & Stokes; and L. W. Robinson) appear in these files along with correspondence from contractors and suppliers of hardware, furniture, and scientific apparatus.
  As in the other sub-series there is correspondence concerning bequests and gifts to the university. Bissell, Carey and Cooke wrote concerning the settlement of the Lampson estate and the firm of Boardman and Boardman handled the Joseph A. Christman estate. Bristol, Stoddard and Bristol advised the university on legal matters including wills. There is a file for the Daniel B. Fayerweather estate, and correspondence with Thomas Thacher concerning the Miriam A. Osborn estate. There is one file about the estate of Thomas G. Sloane. Correspondence with Harper & Brothers and with Francis and Henry Loomis all relates to the Yale treasurer's role as executor of the Elias Loomis estate. The sub-series also includes letters from individuals concerning their contributions to the Alumni University Fund, and from about 1900 - 1901 the files are full of subscriptions to the Yale Bi-centennial Fund. Some of these letters are addressed to Andrew W. Phillips who served as secretary to the Bi-centennial Fund Committee.
  The treasurer corresponded steadily with certain university officials, notably Timothy Dwight, mainly during the president's summer vacation away from the university. Letters were also received from university secretary Anson Phelps Stokes; Simeon Baldwin concerning the law school; George J. Brush, Russell Chittenden, and Henry S. Graves concerning the new forestry school; President Arthur T. Hadley; John F. Weir concerning the school of fine arts; and Robert Brown and W. L. Elkin relating to the university observatory.
  During this period the University created the office of the bursar to relieve the treasurer of many ordinary matters. Correspondence in this sub-series reveals the treasurer still handling some questions concerning student accounts and payments to the faculty and staff. There are also the usual requests for information and applications for employment. During 1901 there were numerous inquiries concerning equipment and staff for the new commons. Correspondence of this routine nature will all be found in the general files in this sub-series.
  1902 - 1906 contains correspondence files maintained for parts of the terms of treasurers Morris Franklin Tyler and Lee McClung. The arbitrary dates of the sub-series correspond with the original office filing scheme. The correspondence, which was originally filed in chronological letter boxes, is now arranged in one alphabetical order with individual files for select correspondents interspersed throughout.
  Many of the topics covered and the correspondents included in this sub-series parallel those in the previous sub-series. Great quantities of investment correspondence are available to the researcher interested in Yale's financial assets in real estate, stocks and bonds. Construction projects begun at the turn of the century reached completion in this period; substantial correspondence with architects, contractors, and equipment suppliers documents these projects, particularly the new commons.
  Aside from the usual correspondence concerning student accounts, internal university finances, and gifts and bequests to the university, there is interesting correspondence relating to the university'srelations with the city of New Haven. Land development in the city limits, police and safety, and taxation of university property are all discussed in these letters.
  From about 1907 through the late 1930s the letters received by the treasurer's office were filed by subject according to a numerical code. This arrangement has been retained for the 156 boxes of correspondence which now comprise Filing Code.
  The filing code was a system that developed over the period of its use. In the beginning the treasurer established several categories of important correspondence and gave each category a number: #3 stood for investments; letters concerning mortgages were filed under #5; and all real estate matters would be found under #10. Sometimes letters prior to 1907 were added to the appropriate code to make a complete subject file. As the treasurer established new categories he gave them the next consecutive number.
  As time went by and new personnel began filing materials according to their own understanding of how the system worked, they introduced many quirks and idiosyncrasies. Code numbers were assigned to very specific categories when general categories were already in existence. Therefore, though #5 contains correspondence on mortgages #47 is the code for mortgages: Nebraska. The creation of numerous small categories such as #319: Night Watchman, 1909 May-Jun, make the system extremely cumbersome; the entire code now runs to 597 numbers. Furthermore, the brief descriptive titles assigned to correspond with the numbers are often too imprecise or vague to make them useful. The use of descriptions like "Motion Pictures" or "Waterproofing" exemplifies this problem.
  The arrangement is not only confusing; it also makes location and retrieval of specific materials very difficult. The researcher is confronted with a long, random list of files which has to be scanned in its entirety to locate all material on a particular subject. Fortunately some cross-referencing has been done in several of the other series to appropriate codes in this sub-series.
  It is unfortunate that the filing system is so peculiar for there is a wealth of information to be found in these files. There is hardly a subject of concern to the university in which the treasurer was not in some way involved and during the majority of this period George Parmly Day, a man active in many phases of university life, served as treasurer. Vast quantities of investment correspondence concerning university-owned real estate, stocks, bonds, other securities, and mortgages, abound in these files. Numerous codes contain material on university benefactors especially relating to estates and to the establishment of scholarships, special funds, and student prizes. In the general area of university administration and operations the researcher will find files for the bursar's office, various departments and schools, and broad files regarding taxes, accounting procedures, and legal affairs, as well as general files for the upkeep of buildings and grounds and files concerning the construction, maintenance, and alterations of individual buildings. Of particular interest are the files at the very end of the sub-series concerning the finances of the Doura-Europos expeditions.
  - 1717-1832
    - 1717-1807 (Box 109, Folder 1)
    - 1811-1816 (Box 109, Folder 2)
    - Concerning mortgage of Dr. Nathan Smith, 1814-1815 (Box 109, Folder 3)
    - 1817-1824 December (Box 109, Folder 4-13)
    - 1825 January-1828 December (Box 110, Folder 14-24)
    - 1829 January-1831 December (Box 111, Folder 25-35)
    - 1832 January-Dec, undated (Box 112, Folder 36-43)
    - Documents concerning Daniel Potter & Others vs. the President and Fellows of Yale College, 1824-1831 (Box 112, Folder 44)
    - Stephen Twining's letterbook, 1806 February 11-1828 January 9, 1832 (Box 112, Folder 45-46)
  - Letterbooks
    - 1833 February 26-1872 January 22 (Box 113, Folder 47-49)
    - 1863 February 23-1894 January 5 (Box 114, Folder 50-53)
    - 1894 January 5-1896 June 19 (Box 115, Folder 54-55)
    - 1896 June 20-1899 February 27 (Box 116, Folder 56-57)
    - 1899 March 2-1900 February 21, 1900 February 23-November 23 (Box 117, Folder 58-59)
    - 1900 November 24-1901 June 25, 1901 June 27-1902 January 10 (Box 118, Folder 60-61)
    - 1902 January 10-1903 May 25 (Box 119, Folder 62-63)
    - 1903 May 25-1905 April 6 (Box 120, Folder 64-65)
    - 1905 April 7-1906 March 28 (Box 121, Folder 66-67)
    - 1906 March 29-October 31 (Box 122, Folder 68-69)
  - Financial Agents' Correspondence
    - Bliss, Seth, 1832 (Box 123, Folder 70)
    - Daggett, David, 1817, 1832 (Box 123, Folder 71)
    - Goodrich, Chauncey A., 1827-1833, 1837, 1840-1841 (Box 123, Folder 72)
    - Mead, Darius, 1831 (Box 123, Folder 73)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, 1831-1833, 1835-1836 (Box 123, Folder 74)
    - Warner, Wyllys: A-D, 1831-1832 (Box 123, Folder 75)
    - Warner, Wyllys: from Seth Bliss, 1832 (Box 123, Folder 76)
    - Warner, Wyllys: from Jeremiah Day (*), 1830-1832 (Box 123, Folder 77)
    - Warner, Wyllys: G-N, 1831-1832 (Box 123, Folder 78)
    - Warner, Wyllys: P-W, unidentified, 1831-1832 (Box 123, Folder 79)
    - Warner, Wyllys: from Benjamin Silliman (*), 1832 (Box 123, Folder 80)
  - 1833-1840
    - Hooker, William G.: correspondence as acting treasurer, 1833-1836 (Box 123, Folder 81)
    - A (Box 123, Folder 82)
    - Ba (Box 123, Folder 83)
    - Be-Bi (Box 123, Folder 84)
    - Bl-Bo (Box 123, Folder 85)
    - Br-Bu (Box 124, Folder 86)
    - Baldwin, Micah, 1834-1840 (Box 124, Folder 87)
    - Barber, Horatio, 1839-1840 (Box 124, Folder 87)
    - Barber, William, 1836-1837 (Box 124, Folder 87)
    - Brown, Abraham, 1833-1840 (Box 124, Folder 87)
    - Ca (Box 124, Folder 88)
    - Ch (Box 124, Folder 89)
    - Cl (Box 124, Folder 90)
    - Co (Box 124, Folder 91)
    - Cr-Cu (Box 124, Folder 92)
    - Champion, Aristarchus, 1833-1834, 1839-1840 (Box 124, Folder 93)
    - Chapin, Oliver, 1836-1838 (Box 124, Folder 93)
    - Chesebrough, Amos S. (*), 1839 (Box 124, Folder 94)
    - Church, Leman, 1835, 1839-1840 (Box 124, Folder 95)
    - Colton, Erastus, 1835-1836 (Box 124, Folder 95)
    - Da-De (Box 124, Folder 96)
    - Di-Dr (Box 124, Folder 97)
    - Du-Dw (Box 125, Folder 98)
    - Day, Jeremiah, 1833-1834 (Box 125, Folder 99)
    - Day, Thomas, 1834, 1836-1837, 1840 (Box 125, Folder 99)
    - Demio, Hiram (*), 1834, 1836-1838, 1840 (Box 125, Folder 100)
    - Doolittle, Mark, 1840 (Box 125, Folder 101)
    - Duncan, Lucius C., 1833-1839 (Box 125, Folder 101)
    - Dyer, Moses, 1839-1840 (Box 125, Folder 101)
    - E (Box 125, Folder 102)
    - Ensign, E. F., 1834 (Box 125, Folder 103)
    - Fa-Fi (Box 125, Folder 104)
    - Fl-Fo (Box 125, Folder 105)
    - Fr-Fu (Box 125, Folder 106)
    - G (Box 125, Folder 107)
    - Ha-Har (Box 125, Folder 108)
    - Has-Hi (Box 125, Folder 109)
    - Hoa-Hoo (Box 125, Folder 110)
    - Hop-How (Box 125, Folder 111)
    - Hub-Hus (Box 125, Folder 112)
    - Hallock, Gerard, 1837-1839 (Box 126, Folder 113)
    - Hooker, William G., 1833-1836, 1839 (Box 126, Folder 113)
    - Hubbard, Richard, 1833-1839 (Box 126, Folder 114)
    - Hubbard, William J., 1835, 1839-1840 (Box 126, Folder 114)
    - Hurlbut, Joseph, 1833, 1835, 1839-1840 (Box 126, Folder 114)
    - I (Box 126, Folder 115)
    - J (Box 126, Folder 116)
    - K (Box 126, Folder 117)
    - Kellogg, Edward (*), 1836, 1839-1840 (Box 126, Folder 118)
    - L (Box 126, Folder 119)
    - Lawrence, William, 1836-1837 (Box 126, Folder 120)
    - Ma (Box 126, Folder 121)
    - Me-Mu (Box 126, Folder 122)
    - Mead, Darius, 1833-1835, 1837, 1840 (Box 126, Folder 123)
    - N (Box 126, Folder 124)
    - O (Box 126, Folder 125)
    - Olcott, Mills (*), 1833-1840 (Box 126, Folder 126)
    - Pa (Box 126, Folder 127)
    - Pe (Box 126, Folder 128)
    - Ph-Pu (Box 126, Folder 129)
    - Perkins, Thomas C., 1833-1834 (Box 127, Folder 130)
    - Ra-Ri (Box 127, Folder 131)
    - Ro-Ru (Box 127, Folder 132)
    - Rockwell, John A., 1834-1840 (Box 127, Folder 133)
    - Rout, Judson A., 1834-1837 (Box 127, Folder 133)
    - Roys, Reuben, 1837-1838 (Box 127, Folder 133)
    - Sa-Sh (Box 127, Folder 134)
    - Si-Sm (Box 127, Folder 135)
    - Sn-Sp (Box 127, Folder 136)
    - St-Sw (Box 127, Folder 137)
    - Silliman, Benjamin D. (*), 1834-1840 (Box 127, Folder 138)
    - Sturdevant, J. M., 1834, 1839 (Box 127, Folder 138)
    - T (Box 127, Folder 139)
    - Talman, Jonathan (*), 1837-1840 (Box 127, Folder 140)
    - Trumbull, John (*), 1833-1837 (Box 127, Folder 141)
    - U (Box 127, Folder 142)
    - V (Box 127, Folder 143)
    - Wa (Box 127, Folder 144)
    - We (Box 127, Folder 145)
    - Wh (Box 128, Folder 146)
    - Wi (Box 128, Folder 147)